<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Will Fondrie</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Will Fondrie</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 08 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>An Intuitive Look at the xcorr Score Function in Proteomics</title>
      <link>/2019/02/an-intuitive-look-at-the-xcorr-score-function-in-proteomics/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/02/an-intuitive-look-at-the-xcorr-score-function-in-proteomics/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to my first blog post! This one is intended for those who are familiar with database searches in proteomics, but want to learn more about how the search engine works.
In proteomics, a database search is one of the most common methods to assign a peptide sequence to an observed mass spectrum. While there are numerous database search algorithms today, all rely on an underlying score function to assess the quality of a peptide-spectrum match (PSM).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/about/</guid>
      <description>Hi, I&amp;rsquo;m Will. I&amp;rsquo;m a computational biologist working as a postdoctoral fellow in Bill Noble&amp;rsquo;s lab at the University of Washington Department of Genome Sciences. My research primarily focuses on employing machine learning to make sense of mass spectrometry data (including, but not limited to proteomics). I received my PhD in 2018 from the University of Maryland, Baltimore, under the direction of Dudley Strickland and David Goodlett.
Outside of science I enjoy good coffee, being outside, playing banjo, and riding my fixed-gear around town.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/pubs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/pubs/</guid>
      <description>Peer-Reviewed Publications 2018  Liang T, Leung LM, Opene B, Fondrie WE, Lee YI, Chandler CE, Yoon SH, Doi Y, Ernst RK, Goodlett DR. (2018) Rapid microbial identification and antibiotic resistance detection by mass spectrometric analysis of membrane lipids. Anal Chem. PMID: 30571097 [PubMed] [Journal Site]
 Fondrie WE, Liang T, Oyler BL, Leung LM, Ernst RK, Strickland DK, Goodlett DR. (2018) Pathogen Identification Direct From Polymicrobial Specimens Using Membrane Glycolipids.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/software/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/software/</guid>
      <description>Software  ppx {python} The ppx package provides a simple means to access the ProteomeXchange repository from Python. Using ProteomeXchange identifiers, the user can retrieve metadata associated with a project and download project files from PRIDE. [GitHub] [Docs] [PyPI]
 pydeck {python} The pydeck package makes it easy to create remark slide decks. This python package handles the boilerplate html needed to create remark slide decks and provides a live reload method for rapid iteration.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/talks/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talks/</guid>
      <description> Recent Talks  Detecting antibiotic resistance by MALDI-TOF analysis of bacterial membrane glycolipids. Fondrie WE, Leung LM, Strickland DK, Ernst RK, Goodlett DR. ASMS Annual Conference on Mass Spectrometry and Allied Topics. June 4, 2017. Indianapolis, IN
 LRP1 modulates TGF-β signaling in the descending thoracic aorta. Fondrie WE, Muratoglu SC, Hampton B, Migliorini M, Galisteo R, Strickland DK. UMB Molecular Medicine Research Retreat. October 6, 2016. Baltimore, MD  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/wordcloud/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/wordcloud/</guid>
      <description>Here’s the code to make my word cloud:
# Code to make the word cloud below # Load packages ---------------------------------------------------------------- suppressMessages(library(tidyverse, quietly = T)) # hide startup message library(tidytext, quietly = T) library(httr, quietly = T) library(xml2, quietly = T) library(wordcloud2, quietly = T) library(webshot) library(htmlwidgets) set.seed(9621) # for reproducibility # Query pubmed using Entrez eutils ---------------------------------------------- queryBase &amp;lt;- c(&amp;quot;https://eutils.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/eutils/&amp;quot;) # get UIDs for articles uids &amp;lt;- GET(paste0(queryBase, &amp;quot;esearch.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>